Guide to the B. D. Amis Papers TAM.355
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
B. D. Amis Papers
1930-2004, (Bulk 1930-1949)
1930-1949
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Amis, B. D., b. 1896
Amis Bell, Debbie
TAM.355
2 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
B. D. Amis (1896-1993), was an African-American Communist and labor union organizer. He was a leader of the American Negro Labor Congress, the League of Struggle for Negro Rights, and the National Negro Congress, three Communist Party-inspired popular front organizations. He was a Party organizer for District Six, headquartered in Cleveland. He then moved to Philadelphia, where he was an organizer for the Steel Workers Organizing Committee and chairman of the Philadelphia Committee for the Defense of Ethiopia, and went on to organize Catering Industry Employees Union, Local 758, an African-American local within the Hotel and Restaurant Employees and Bartenders International Union (AFL), serving as Secretary-Treasurer of both organizations, ca. 1939-1942. The collection consists mostly of published and unpublished writings, many of them written for the Daily Worker, for the monthly journal, Communist, or for the international Communist movement weekly, International Press Correspondence (aka Inprecorr). Also included are reports to various Communist Party national and local bodies, most of which are concerned with the struggle for African-American civil rights and the Communist Party's positions on civil rights issues. There are also clippings by and about Amis, correspondence, including a letter from African-American Communist leader Benjamin J. Davis, radio speeches, copies of photographs of Amis and of political meetings, and collective bargaining agreements signed by Amis.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Debbie Amis Bell in 2006. The accession number associated with this gift is 2006.010.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into one series:
Missing Title
I, Papers, 1930-2004.
Historical/Biographical Note
B. D. (B. DeWayne) Amis, 1896-1993, was an African-American Communist Party USA and labor union organizer. Amis was born in Chicago and by 1928 was president of the NAACP branch in Peoria, IL, when the Communist Party invited him to come to New York. Amis became a member of the National Committee of the Communist-inspired American Negro Labor Congress, and also wrote articles for the Daily Worker, the party newspaper. In 1930, Amis became general secretary of the Communist-inspired League of Struggle for Negro Rights (LSNR) and an editor of its publication, The Liberator. During this period Amis wrote the pamphlets Lynch Justice at Work (1930) and They shall not die!: The story of Scottsboro in pictures (1932). Amis went on to become the District Organizer for the Communist Party in Cleveland and traveled to the Soviet Union on two occasions, the second time for about a year and a half. While there, he took courses in Marxism and wrote articles for the Negro Worke r, the newspaper of the International Trade Union Committee of Negro Workers.
Upon his return to the United States, Amis settled in Philadelphia where he joined the Steel Workers Organizing Committee (SWOC) as a field organizer. He was also the head of the Philadelphia committee of the National Negro Congress, and the chairman of the Philadelphia Committee for the Defense of Ethiopia. He ran as the Communist candidate for Auditor General of Pennsylvania in 1936. He went on to organize Catering Industry Employees Union, Local 758, an African-American local of the Hotel and Restaurant Employees and Bartenders International Union (AFL), serving as Secretary-Treasurer of both organizations, ca. 1939-1942. He subsequently worked for the Gulf Oil Company, while continuing his union and community organizing activities. Amis died in 1993.
Sources:
B. D. Amis - Black Communist and Labor Leader, by his son Barry D. Amis, People's Weekly World, Nov. 20, 2004. (http://www.pww.org/index.php/article/articleview/6137/1/241/)
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists mostly of published and unpublished writings, many of them written for the Daily Worker, for the monthly journal, Communist, or for the international Communist movement weekly, International Press Correspondence. Also included are reports to various Communist Party national and local bodies, including reports to District Six (headquartered in Cleveland, Ohio), for which he served as the District Organizer and a report detailing the Communist movement's activities in the city of Rockford, Ohio, as well as radio speeches, some relating to Amis' labor and Communist Party activism in Eastern Pennsylvania. There are also several collective bargaining agreements signed by Amis on behalf of the Local Joint Board of Philadelphia, consisting of Local 758 and several other locals of the Hotel and Restaurant Employees' International Alliance and Bartenders' International Union (AFL). The majority of Amis' writings relate to the struggle for Africa-American civil rights, and the Communist Party's positions on civil rights issues. There is also a file relating to the Philadelphia Committee for the Defense of Ethiopia, a file relating to his candidacy for the office of Auditor General of Pennsylvania, clippings, letters to Amis from Philadelphia government officials in response to his queries about community issues, a 1947 letter from Ben Davis, copies of photographs, and a copy of a 2004 biographical article by his son, Barry D. Amis, published in the Communist Party's newspaper, the People's Weekly World.
Black-and-white photographs.; Clippings (information artifacts); Communism |z Pennsylvania.; Speeches.; Correspondence.; Collective labor agreements.; Reports.; Manuscripts for publication.; Race relations in the United States.; African American labor union members.; Hospitality industry |x Employees |x Labor unions |z Pennsylvania.; Pennsylvania |x Social conditions.; African American communists.; Rockford (Ohio) |x Social conditions.; African Americans -- Civil rights.; Communism |z Ohio.; African American labor leaders.; Italo-Ethiopian War, 1935-1936 |x Foreign public opinion, American.; Communism -- United States.; National Negro Congress (U.S.); Hotel and Restaurant Employees International Alliance; Hotel Employees & Restaurant Employees International Union; Philadelphia Committee for the Defense of Ethiopia; Communist Party of the United States of America; Catering Industry Employees Union. Local 758; Amis, B. D., b. 1896; American Negro Labor Congress; Communist Party of the United States of America (Penn.); League of Struggle for Negro Rights (U.S.); Davis, Benjamin J. (Benjamin Jefferson), 1903-1964; Amis Bell, Debbie
- Series I: Papers, 1930-2004.
  - Biographical: People's Weekly World Article by Barry D. Amis (son of B. D. Amis), Nov 20, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Cards: Business, Identification, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Catering Industry Employees' Union No. 758 (B. D. Amis, Secretary-Treasurer) Correspondence, Reports, 1939-1942, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Communist Party USA District Six: Next Steps in the Struggles for Winter Relief, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Davis, Benjamin: Letter to B. D. Amis, Sep 4, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Edelman, John W., CIO Regional Director (Eastern Pennsylvania): Letter of Reference for B. D. Amis, Dec 3, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ethiopia, The Philadelphia Committee for the Defense of, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - International Press Correspondence: Articles by B. D. Amis, 1931, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letters to B.D. Amis (re Community Organizing), 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - National Negro Oppression and Social Antagonism, by B. D. Amis (photocopy), The Communist, No. 9, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Newspaper Articles by/about B.D. Amis, 1931-1942, Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Pamphlets by B. D. Amis (photocopies): Lynch Justice at Work, They Shall Not Die; plus Typescripts of Introductions, 1930, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Photographs (copies), 1932, Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Radio Speeches (Candidate for Auditor General, Pennsylvania), 1936 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Report on Rockford (Ohio) Situation by B. D. Amis, CPUSA Organizer, Rockford., Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Report to the District Convention (CPUSA, Eastern Pennsylvania), Jun 1936 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Report to Communist Party USA, 7th Convention, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Restaurant Employees International Alliance and Bartenders (AFL): Contracts Signed by B. D. Amis, Secretary-Treasurer, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Reports to Communist Party USA: Plenums, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Reports to Communist Party USA: Plenums, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Report Executive Committee of the Communist International: Situation and Tasks of the American Party and the Cleveland District, Apr 1, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Steel Workers Organizing Committee (Pennsylvania), Reports on by B. D. Amis, Undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Sun Shipbuilding and Dry Duck Co. (Chester, PA): B. D. Amis Letters Seeking Employment, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Writings, Published (Typescript): "Building of a Mass Organization." (St. Louis), Nov 16, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Writings, Published (Typescript): "Croppers in Southern United States Fight to Live." (Inprecorr), Undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Writings, Published (Typescript): "Daily Worker Leads Fight for May Day.", Undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Writings, Published (Typescript): "The Dies Bill - A Part of Capitalist Drive." (Uj Elore - Hungarian-American Communist newspaper), Undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Writings, Published (Typescript): "For a Strict Leninist Analysis of the Negro National Question in the United States." (Communis t), Oct 1932 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Writings, Published (Typescript): "How We Carried Out the Decision of the 1930 Communist International Resolution on the Negro Question in the United States." (Communist International, no. 9), May 5, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Writings, Published (Typescript): "Marion Demonstrates American Democracy.", Undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Writings, Published (Typescript): "National Negro Congress Writes Page in the History of Race People." (Philadelphia Tribune), Feb 27, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Writings, Published (Typescript): "The National Recovery Act Lynch Drive Calls for Mass Resistance." (Inprecorr), Feb 9, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Writings, Published (Typescript): "Need of Clarity.", Undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Writings, Published (Typescript): "The Negro National Oppression and Social Antagonisms.", Undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Writings, Published (Typescript): "Opportunism on March 28th Demonstrations." (Communist), Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Writings, Published (Typescript): "Our Fraction Work in the ANCL (American Negro Labor Congress)." (Party Organizer), Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Writings, Published (Typescript): "Reply to an Arrogant Yankee." (Daily Worker), Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Writings, Published (Typescript): "Smashing Bourgeois Barriers in Southern United States." (Inprecorr), Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Writings, Published (Typescript): "Struggle Against White Chauvinism." (Daily Worker), Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Writings, Published (Typescript): "Vote Communist - Negro Workers!" (Daily Worker), Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Writings, Published (Typescript): "We Demand Unemployment Insurance." (Editorial, Liberator), Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Writings, Unpublished: "For A Strict Leninist Analysis of the Negro National Question In the United States.", Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Writings, Unpublished: "Lynch Justice at Work.", Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Writings, Unpublished: Miscellaneous Untitled Works, Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Writings, Unpublished: "A Point Gained From the Party National Convention.", Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Writings, Unpublished: "Some Serious Questions Concerning Our Negro Work in the Philadelphia District.", Undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Writings, Unpublished: "They Refuse to Starve.", Undated (Box 2, Folder 13)